<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iudgement of that reuerend and Godly lerned man, M. Lambert Danæus, touching certaine points now in controuersie, contained in his preface before his commentary vpon the first Epistle to Timothie, written in Latine, and dedicated by him to the Prince of Orange. But novv translated into Englishe, for the behofe and comfort of all those, who (not vnderstanding the Latine tongue) are desirous to know the trueth in those points</title>
            <title>In D. Pauli priorem epistolam ad Timotheum commentarius. English. dedication</title>
            <author>Daneau, Lambert, ca. 1530-1595?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111042</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846469</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11438</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19800)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11438)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 213:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iudgement of that reuerend and Godly lerned man, M. Lambert Danæus, touching certaine points now in controuersie, contained in his preface before his commentary vpon the first Epistle to Timothie, written in Latine, and dedicated by him to the Prince of Orange. But novv translated into Englishe, for the behofe and comfort of all those, who (not vnderstanding the Latine tongue) are desirous to know the trueth in those points</title>
                  <title>In D. Pauli priorem epistolam ad Timotheum commentarius. English. dedication</title>
                  <author>Daneau, Lambert, ca. 1530-1595?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Waldegrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of the dedication of Daneau, Lambert. In D. Pauli priorem epistolam ad Timotheum commentarius.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>The end of text is dated: Geneva 1577, as in Daneau's original work--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church discipline --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11438:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11438:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IVDGEMENT OF THAT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND AND GODLY LERNED MAN, M. LAMBERT DANAEVS, TOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching certaine points now in controuerſie, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his preface before his commentary vpon the firſt Epiſtle to Timothie, written in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and dedicated by him to the Prince of Orange.</p>
            <p>BVT NOVV TRANSLATED IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO ENGLISHE, FOR THE BEHOFE and comfort of all thoſe, who (not vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Latine tongue) are deſirous to know the trueth in thoſe points.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11438:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11438:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, WILLIAM Prince of Orange, Earle of Naſſaw, the moſt vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant maintainer &amp; defender of Chriſts glorie, in Holland and Zeland: grace and peace from the Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an olde ſaying, (moſt noble prince) vſed alſo of Ariſtotle, that there is nothing more beutifull in the whol frame of nature then comlineſſe and good order. For what confuſed and diſorderlye thing can be pleaſant to the eye,<note place="margin">Order how neceſſary.</note> or delightſome vnto the minde of man? verely nothing at al. And in deede if theſe things that either we looke vpon with the eies of our bodie, or conſider with the faculties of our minde, ſeeme vnto vs neither to be orderly diſpoſed, nor to cleaue together by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny comodious ſituation: nor ordered by any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ſeemely maner, wee preſently giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that they haue neither profit, nor delight in them. And wee doe noe leſſe abhorre ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comly ſightes, then we delight to look vpon thoſe things which are diſtinguiſhed into their natural and proper parts. And this that I ſpeake is verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be true in kingdoms, in common wealthes,
<pb facs="tcp:11438:3"/>in townes, in vilages, in priuat houſes, in gardens, in feildes, in wilderneſſes, and in whatſoeuer ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature bringeth forth, or mans wit and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie inuenteth: as not only experience it ſelfe, but euen the common voice of al men, both godly &amp; prophane doth witneſſe. To be briefe, the world it ſelfe being the moſt beutifull worke of Gods owne hand, is of the Grecians called κοσμος for the order and comlineſſe that is therein.</p>
            <p>Whereby their opinion apeareth to be moſt deteſtable,<note place="margin">Order or beauty.</note> which not only delight them ſelues in diſorder &amp; confuſion: but alſo (by remouing of al good order) do indeuor to turn euery thing vpſide down, &amp; to induce a generall mixture of al things both priuat &amp; publick. The which ſort of men, as being the monſters &amp; common plagues of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the Auncients were wont to cal vnruly and vnbrideled ſpirits. But concerning comlines and good order, this we are to thinke of it, that as the ſame is not onely profitable, but alſo moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary euery where: ſoe eſpecially ought it to haue place in the church of God, as the Apoſtle Paule by expreſſe commaundement doth teach vs.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.40.</note> For the church is the houſe of God, that great King of Kinges. Wherein therefore al things ought to be done circumſpectly, ſeemly, and decently, &amp; as Paul him ſelfe ſpeketh,<note place="margin">The diſho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor of god ioyned with the diſorder of the Church.</note> honeſtly and according vnto good order, but nothing confuſedly &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, leaſt the diſorder of the houſe be a ſtaine, and a diſhonor vnto the Maieſty of the houſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him ſelfe, who is the great and the mightie
<pb facs="tcp:11438:3"/>God. And to this purpoſe he himſelfe of his great mercie hath preſcribed in his worde, not onely thoſe things, which are neceſſarie to eternall life, and concearne the ground-worke and ſaluation of his Church: But alſo hath manifeſted thoſe pointes which are behoofefull vnto the right go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement and beautie of his Church, leaſt there ſhuld be any thing appertaining to the right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of his houſe, whereof, we ſhould not be fully and ſufficiently inſtructed out of his owne mouth. And to the end that thoſe rules which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto the regiment of the church, ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, bee ſeuered and diſtinguiſhed, from thoſe pointes which containe the doctrine of iuſtifiyng faith, they are generally called of all men,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</note> by the name of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline. For euen as that part of gods word, and the knowledge of his truth, which teacheth vs what we are to beleeue, concerning God the Father, concerning Chriſt, together with his natures and offices, concerning the holy Ghoſt, concerning the cauſes of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and concerning eternal life, doth containe the very bones and ſinows, and as it were, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eſſence of the body of the church. So the ſame part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, which ſetteth downe the rules of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline, doth make vp the ornamentes and iewels of the body of the church, whereby it is attired, and without which it is no other, then a body naked, and without cloathing. So that hereby we may ſee, what a nere conjunction and agreement there is betweene
<pb facs="tcp:11438:4"/>theſe two, to wit, betweene the doctrine and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Church. For except you joine ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical diſcipline, vnto the light &amp; profeſſion of the truth, an aſſembly of men, euen embraſing the purity of the word preached, ſhalbe nothing, but a naked body bereaued and deſtitute of al at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and ornaments. And therefore is this eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical diſcipline rightly tearmed by ſome of the Ancient fathers, to be the keeper of the doctrine of faith, the mother of vertue, the bond of hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and the very ſinewe of chriſtian ſociety. The force whereof indeede, is ſo greate, that it alone bringeth vnto the church, whatſoeuer we account to be the comlineſſe, beuty, brightnes, and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, and it maketh the ſame ſo pleaſant vnto the eies, that (as Tertullian ſaith) the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes (which were alwaies the greateſt and moſt deadly enemies thereof) did ſpitefully cal eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical diſcipline, a baite to enſnare, and alure men to loue the church.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</note>Seeing therefore this diſcipline is a rule and a parte of that juſtice, whereby the outwarde order and the lawful gouernment of the whole church is contained: who are they that with any coulor can pretend, that ether the ſame is to be deſpiſed, or not to be labored for? VVhoſe inſtitution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan not firſt vnder the newe Teſtament, but was firſt ordained vnder the lawe by God himſelfe, as that worthie profeſſor of the Hebrue tongue, and my fellow laborer, Cornelius Bertram, hath long ſince very learnedly taught in his booke concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:11438:4"/>the pollicy of the Iewes. For what els but the preſcribing of eccleſiaſtical diſcipline doe the lawes of God meane, which diſtinguiſhe the tribe of Leuie from al other tribes, that out of it onely, the miniſters of the temple ſhoulde be choſen, &amp; within the ſame tribe, doe ſeuere the office of the prieſt from the Leuits, &amp; ſet downe what was the authority both of the high prieſt, and of the reſt of thoſe that had to doe with the prieſthood. And what els doe theſe lawes meane, which ſette down, what rites and drinke offrings were requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in euery kinde of ſacrifice? To conclude the whole ceremonial lawe appointed by the Lorde him ſelfe, what els I praye you is it, but a moſt ample and a moſt cleare deſcription of eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſcipline? And as the Lord was not ſparing in the inſtitution hereof, vnder the olde teſtament, ſoe hath hee as largely vnder the newe, inſtituted (or rather reſtored it being fallen downe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed) the ſame by his Apoſtles, as being a matter altogether moſt neceſſary for the right conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and gouernement of his Church. The which thing appeareth out of many places in the newe teſtament, and eſpecially out of the Acts of the Apoſtles the firſt epiſtle of Paul to the Corin. the firſt to Timothie, and that to Titus. In al which, &amp; the like places, whatſoeuer apertaines to the right and laweful gouernement of the Church is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and largely ſet downe: Whether you regard the ordering of the whole Church in general, or the gouerning of ſome fewe in particular. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb facs="tcp:11438:5"/>whereof, I thinke it a wonderful &amp; an abſurde caſe, that afterwards ſo many cannons, ſo many decrees of ſynods, ſo many conſtitutions of churches,<note place="margin">The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and prouinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels for the moſt part vaine and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</note> both general and particular, were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and eſtabliſhed for the ordering of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal gouernement. For what neede was there of this labour? which only did ariſe from the greate contempt, and ignorance of theſe precepts, which the holy Ghoſt had ſet downe by the pen of the Apoſtles, and that becauſe men deſpiſed the waies of God, that they might eſtabliſh the inuentions of their owne braynes, and bring into the church their owne tradicions, which for the moſt part, were too abſurde and childiſh, and alwaies mere contrary vnto the Diſcipline preſcribed in the worde of God.</p>
            <p>But here ſome man wil demaund, whether this diſcipline be ſo preciſely ſet downe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the newe teſtament, as nothing can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto it, and apointed ſo ſtrictly vnder paine of the Lords diſpleaſure, as men may not ſwerue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit at al from it? In the anſwere of this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I muſt be faine to vſe a diſtinction. For there are many and ſundry partes of Eccleſiaſtical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline: whereof the one doth containe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe only a general way and meane of placing, guiding, and ruling the Church, in whatſoeuer place and country of the world it doth remaine. As for example, that only the voice of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt is to be harde in the church, and no other. That the ſacraments are only to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:11438:5"/>vnto the godly, and faythfull, and all other pointes that are of like kinde, which generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the conſeruation of the Church. The other parte doth handle, and declare more particularly the rule of gouerning the ſame. This latter parte of Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline containeth 4. heades. Firſt the election of theſe perſons, which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto ſome Eccleſiaſticall office. Secondlye, a deſcription of the offices and callings of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are elected? Thirdly, the way and maner of adminiſtring church cenſures, as wel publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the aſſembly of the elders, as otherwiſe. The fourth is concerning the receiuing into the Church, of them that are vnder the eccleſiaſticall cenſures, either ſuſpended, or excommunicated. When as the queſtion is therfore, whether euery particular of theſe heades, be ſo ſet downe in the word, that nothing can be added thereunto.<note place="margin">Some things eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall, ſome things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentarie in the regi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the church</note> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that in euery worke, cauſe, and action, there are ſome things eſſential, and ſome thinges acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental. Thoſe thinges are eſſential, which contain the whol nature of the thing, or ſome parte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as in this argument. If any man in the laweful calling of Paſtors or other church officers, that are to be choſen ſhal deny, either that their life and doctrine are to be tryed: or that the approbation of the people, is to be had in their choiſe, he deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thoſe things which are eſſential vnto al lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful elections. In like ſort, if any man ſhal ſay that this tryal is not to be had by the church, and that by many: but by one man alone, and ſhall teache
<pb facs="tcp:11438:6"/>that the Church is to ſtande in this caſe vnto the meare determination of one, he taketh away thoſe things which are eſſential in election. But if a man ſhoulde reaſon, that this tryall by many is to bee done in this or that place, at this or that time, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this or that maner, he ſpeaketh only of thoſe things which are accidental. As for example, the ancient manner in times paſt of election, and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of Paſtors was, that he ſhoulde be choſen by 3. Biſhops, or Paſtors that were next vnto him, togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Elderſhip, and church whereof hee was to be Paſtor. And this was done onely in the metropolitan City, at a certaine and an apointed time, namely in the time of publicke faſt: to bee ſhort, he was choſen not by the bare conſent, and voice of the people, but by the lifting vp of their hands which was called χεῖ̓ροτονία, al which things are to be accounted accidentarie, and not eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in election. This therefore wee conclude, that whatſoeuer by the word of God is commanded to be done and obſerued in the gouernment of the church, whether it be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> election, or the offices of thoſe that are called, or whatſoeuer head of eccleſiaſtical diſcipline it doth reſpect: we conclude I ſay, that to be altogether eſſential. But as for thoſe thinges which are adjudged, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in euery particular prouince, or Church, to be moſt commodious to effect, and practiſe the former points, we hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be but accidentary matters. As that the preaching of the word ſhold be at this hower, rather then at an other. That the
<pb facs="tcp:11438:6"/>church ſhould rather haue this number of Elders and deacons, then that. Al which things are to be held accidentary, &amp; in no wiſe eſſential vnto the gouerment of the Church.</p>
            <p>Nowe therefore vnto the preſent queſtion in hand, according vnto this diſtinction wee anſwer after this ſorte, that wee vtterly holde it vnlawful, that ſuch things as are eſſentiall vnto Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, ſhould be either augmented or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, by the commandements &amp; lawes of men. But as for the things that are accidental wee deny not, but they may be increaſed, diminiſhed, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied or augmented, not only by euery prouince, but euen by particular Churches, as they finde them conuenient, or incommodious vnto their ſtate, and to ſpeake in a word, as occaſion of the circumſtances of places, times, and perſons, ſhall require.</p>
            <p>And after the ſelfe ſame manner, wee anſwere vnto that other demaunde of ſome, which would know, whether the Church may ſwarue from that order of gouernement, which is ſet downe in the writings of the Apoſtles, and whether the one &amp; the ſelfe ſame forme of Church regiment &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, ought to be eſtabliſhed in al the churches that profeſſe the Goſpell? For, if they ſpeake of thoſe thinges which are eſſential vnto the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the church, the anſwer is, that al churches are bound alike to obſerue and keepe them inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable, as that the gouernement of the Church ſhoulde be Ariſtocratical, that is in the handes of
<pb facs="tcp:11438:7"/>many, and not monarchical, that is in the handes of one, and that euery congregation ſhould haue in it a Senate or company of Elders,<note place="margin">Al chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches therefore are bound to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the elderſhip.</note> choſe by the church, without whom, neither the Paſtor, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man els, is to deale in the affairs of the church, and that in euery congregation, there bee ſome cenſuring of wickednes, and of vnruly manners, which cenſures are not to be adminiſtred, by the arbitriment of one man: but by the deliberation and judgment of the leaders, and gouerners, and as Ierom ſaith, of the Elders of the church. To be ſhort, it is eſſential vnto eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, that the ſentence of excommunication bee giuen forth againſt the obſtinat, and that it be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, not according to the minde and judgement of ciuilians, and ſuch as giue ſentence according vnto the lawes of man: but by the direction of the officers of the church, which judge acording vnto the lawes of God, and that it be giuen forth, not in a corner by one man alone: but by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and in the preſence of the Church, the ſame <q rend="margDblQuotes">being gathered together for that purpoſe. And therefore wee anſwere plainly and directly, that the ſubſtance, or eſſential partes of eccleſiaſtical diſcipline, ought to be the ſame, in al the churches that profeſſe the Goſpel, or cary the name of any reformation with them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But if the queſtion bee concerning outwarde things, which only are accidentary vnto this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, wherin onely the conuenience or diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity ſtandeth in the practiſe, or the omitting of
<pb facs="tcp:11438:7"/>ſome thinges indifferent, wee holde that thoſe pointes may bee changeable: yea and that often times it is requiſite they ſhoulde bee changed, in conſideration of the reſpect, that is to be had, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diuerſitie of times, places &amp; perſons. So far are wee in this point, from requiring that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry countrey and region ſhoulde be tyed vnto the ſame forme of outwarde order. For it may fal out that theſe thinges which in this place, and in this countrey is wel and commodiouſly done. (As for example, the lords ſupper is adminiſtred in France once euery quarter) cannot bee ſo conueniently practiſed in other regions and countries. After this manner it is, that the ſentence of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication in ſom places is red out of booke, which in other Churches is denounced by the Paſtor, as the Lord directeth him to ſpeake for the preſent time. Euen ſo alſo, the maner is in this Church of Geneua, that he who hath fallen to Idolatry, and deſireth afterwardes to bee reconciled vnto the Church, maketh confeſſion of his fault vpon the Lords day onely: whereas in other Churches, he might doe it at any other day, that the Churche thinketh conuenient. Here with vs the penitent readeth his confeſſion, in other places he ſpeaketh it, as he is moued for the preſent. Al theſe indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things then may haue a diuers forme, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diuerſity of places &amp; times, &amp;c: ſo that alwaies the correction of manners, the acknowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the fault, the ſeperation of the goates from the ſheepe, be retained in the lordes houſe, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11438:8"/>thoſe thinges done, which God requireth to bee put in execution. And ſo this point be euermore practiſed, that the Church and houſe of God bee orderly gouerned, that it may appeare not to be a cadge of vncleane birdes, but the well gouerned familie of the liuing God.</p>
            <p>The ſubſtance therefore and eſſential partes of diſcipline, ought to bee one and the ſelfe ſame, in al the Churches of God in what age or place ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they bee, but as for ſuch thinges as are acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentary thereunto, they may bee changed. And therefore in this queſtion, wee holde it needefull that men ſhould learne alwaies to make a diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene the accidentall and the eſſentiall partes of Church diſcipline. Furthermore, we <q rend="margDblQuotes">ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it meerely vnlaweful, that any man, yea the ſupreame Magiſtrate, or yet the vniuerſal body of the true Church, ſhould goe about to change,</q> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, remoue, diminiſh or augment any thing that is Eſſentiall in Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in ciuil cauſes the King,<note place="margin">The go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the church not to bee changed.</note> or the chiefe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, may by vertue of the authority graunted vnto him by the Lord, make newe lawes, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate the olde: yet notwithſtanding he hath not the like authoritie, either in aboliſhing and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, the eſſential parts of eccleſiaſtical diſcipline, or yet in adding any thing of his own thereunto. The reaſon whereof is moſt manifeſt and cleare. For ſeeing the eſpecial ſcope, and end of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Diſcipline is: firſt, that the Paſtors which take charge of Gods people, haue a laweful cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.
<pb facs="tcp:11438:8"/>Secondly that the conſciences of men bee ruled, and by true conuerſion and repentance, brought vnto the obedience of Gods wil: it muſt needs follow, that the ordaining &amp; appointing of eccleſiaſtical diſcipline is only in the Lords hand: becauſe that he alone is the Lord, king, ruler and lawgiuer of his Church, and hee alone, the onely true and lawful iudge, and gouernour of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men. And therefore hee alone, is both to preſcribe the rules of the lawfull callings, of ſuch as are to beare office in his houſe, and alſo to ſet downe the way, howe the conſciences of men may bee mooued, and repentaunce wrought in them. In which two points (as we haue ſayd) the chiefe force and drift of Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline is contained. And concerning theſe matters, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther king, nor yet the whole body of the Church, haue authority to preſcribe any other lawes then thoſe, which Chriſt himſelfe hath ſet downe. For the Church it ſelfe is no other then a ſeruaunt, to be ruled by the commaundements of God hir ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lorde, and not a Queene, or a Lady to preſcribe vnto her ſelfe, what lawe ſhe likes beſt, and as for Kings and Princes, they are members and not heads of the Church, members indeede, that are to be reuerenced aboue the reſt, in reſpect of their calling, yet members in ſuch ſort, as in the gouerning of the Churche, they are not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund as they liſt: but their duety is onely to be carefull, that the commaundements of the Lord may bee put in execution, by, and amongeſt their
<pb facs="tcp:11438:9"/>ſubiectes. For out of all controuerſie, the Lorde alone is to appoint and ordaine Eccleſiaſticall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and callinges, as hee is the onely ſearcher and ruler of the ſoule and conſcience. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſeeing the ruling of the conſciences of men, and the ſubduing of them vnto the obedience of God, is the end wherefore Eccleſiaſticall Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline is ordained: The way and the means, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that worke is to be effected, can be ſhewed by none, ſaue onely by the Lorde alone, becauſe hee only made and formed the conſcience and mind of man, he only knoweth how they may be ruled, turned and changed: and he onely is the Lord of them. Whence it is, that to ſeeke any where els (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially from the mouth of natural man) ſaue on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly at the word of God, the laws to rule and guide the conſcience, is nothing els, but to hunt after er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and deluſions, and to offer extreame injurie vnto the maieſty of God, which claimeth this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority vnto himſelfe alone. We do not deny, but that kings and Princes together with their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, and ſuch as are well ſeene in matters of ſtate may deuiſe and enact wholſome lawes for the maintaining of publicke peace among their ſubiects: but to inuent and ordaine newe lawes (beſides thoſe that are preſcribed in Gods word) wherewith they would rule and binde the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men, or to appoint &amp; enact ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and conſtitutions, concerning the lawful cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of thoſe that gouerne the Church, (which is the houſe of God, and not the manſion of anie
<pb facs="tcp:11438:9"/>earthly Prince) they haue no warrant nor autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie at all. Yea, (and as hath bene ſayd) the whole Church of God, gathered and aſſembled togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a generall Councell, hath no authoritie at all, to take any ſuch worke in hand. In ſo much as, whatſoeuer generall Councels haue enacted and conſtituted different from, or contrary vnto the ſubſtance of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the worde of God, it was nothing els, but plaine tyrannie, and a moſt injurious vſurpation of the right which belongeth vnto the Lorde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, although it cannot bee denied, but thoſe Councels and aſſemblies perſwaded themſelues that they went about no ſuch matter, but inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a farre better, and a more holie purpoſe. The confuſion, and miſerable ruine of the Church, folowed vpon their purpoſes, do manifeſtly ſhew the truth hereof. For if they had retained that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline of the Apoſtles, and appointed no other, the Church of God had not fallen into that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible diſorder, wherewith, at the length, it was la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably ouerthrowen.</p>
            <p>Doe you then, will ſome men ſay, condemne all thoſe Churches, that receiued the goſpell, wherein, either no Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline at all, or at the leaſt, that ordained by the Apoſtles, is not obſerued, but haue either corrupted the true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, or ſubſtituted a falſe, in ſtead thereof. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this odious queſtion, wherewith we haue bene often cumbred, wee anſwere plainely, and yet lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly and modeſtly, that we indeed do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
<pb facs="tcp:11438:10"/>thoſe Churches and congregations, wher idolatry is baniſhed, and the pure and true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell retained, as not beeing the Churches of GOD: notwithſtanding, that they want and in joy not the true gouerenment of the Church. For the fundamentall, and true, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible note of gods Church heere vpon earth, is onely one, namely, the word of God truly prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by a lawful Paſtor, the which true preaching of the worde, whereſoeuer it bee, there men may boldly conclude, the Lordes flocke to bee a rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, according to the ſaying of our ſauior Chriſt, My ſheepe heare my voyce: yea, and wee hould this flocke to bee the flocke of God, although it want both the adminiſtration of the ſacraments, and the vſe and practiſe of the true Diſcipline of the Church. And whereas theſe 2. laſt markes, to wit, the ſacraments, and diſcipline, are by ſome thought neceſſary to point out the true Church, their meaning in this, is nothing els, but to ſhew what and how much is neceſſarily required, to the perfect and abſolute conſtitution of the outward face of a Churche. But they are verye farre from thinking that thoſe congregations cannot be at al accounted the Churches of God, which want ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall diſcipline, ſo that the word of God be trulie and ſoundly preached in them. Thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations and aſſemblies then, which want Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, are indeed the Churches of God, but yet lame, vnperfect and maimed Churches. As we cal him a man, though he haue both his arms cut off,
<pb facs="tcp:11438:10"/>ſo that hee be liuing &amp; haue the vſe of his reaſon. Notwithſtanding, all thoſe Countries, who (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing baniſhed idolatry, and receiued the true and liuely word of God) do as yet want this diſciplin, ought to know, that this ſhuld be their chiefe care and continual endeuor, euen that they may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, joyne and adde vnto their Church this notable ornament, namely, Eccleſiaſticall Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, as it is preſcribed in the writinges of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and ſo they ſhall not only haue the bones and ſinowes, but inioy the bloud, colour, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and retaine the abſolute ſtrength of a Church. And in this point, that ſpeeche of the holy ghoſt, is carefully to be hearkned vnto, that we ought to make ſtraight ſteps vnto our feet, leaſt that which halteth, be at length clean turned out of the way. For if thoſe things which are needful, be through careleſneſſe neglected in the Church of God, it will come to paſſe, that in proceſſe of time, the Church it ſelfe, wil be clean alienated from God. And in aſmuch as this Diſcipline whereof wee ſpeake, is ſet downe in the firſt Epiſtle of Tim. therfore I haue principally choſen it, in the expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding wherof, I thought good, briefly to ſet down my iudgement concerning this whole argument. Diuers &amp; many, both new and olde writers, being indeed learned men, haue written vpon this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: But amongſt the reſt, one Claudius Spenſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, eſpecially endeuoured to ſhew, how much he was able to write, concerning the Diſcipline of the Church. For beſides a large commentarie
<pb facs="tcp:11438:11"/>that he hath written vpon the text it ſelfe, he hath alſo publiſhed no leſſe then three tedious books of digreſſions (as he calleth them) vpon this verie ſame Epiſtle. But he is ſo farre in my iudgement, from being a helpe vnto any man by his bookes, that in my daies, I haue knowen nothing more obſcure, then his verie commentary, and nothing more confuſed, and out of order, then are his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate diſcourſes. For theſe Schoolmen, of whoſe number this Spenſaeus was on, are blinded by the iuſt iudgement of God, and ſo giuen to obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that in the moſt thinges they vnderſtand not themſelues, becauſe their onely bringing vp is in darknes, and vaine iangling. Indeed, when I had lighted vpon theſe commentaries, and could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit my ſelfe nothing at all by them, the beſt courſe that I could take, was to betake me from his wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dering digreſſions, vnto the right way it ſelfe, that is, vnto the text of the Apoſtle, and ſo as the olde prouerbe faith, I dranke, and haſted away. For my ſelfe, what I haue attained vnto by this my trauel, and howe much I haue manifeſted this cauſe, which otherwiſe, for want of practiſe, nowe theſe many yeares was growen out of vſe, &amp; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of men, let others iudge. Thus much I may bouldlye affirme, that I was not able to bring to light theſe olde rubuſhes of antiquitie without great labour, and paines. Howſoeuer it bee, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the Lord God, that theſe my labours may be profitable vnto his Church: and acceptable vnto the godly.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11438:11"/>
            <p>And as for your excellency (moſt noble prince) vnto whome I doe moſt humbly, and willinglie dedicate this worke, if it may bee but approoued of you, I ſhal take your acceptation, as a great fruit of the labour beſtowed heerein. There are many and diuerſe cauſes of waight, why, I ſhould dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this trauel of mine vnto your excellency, but this in ſpeciall. And that is, that whereas, by the bleſsing of GOD, and your great wiſedome, and ſtrength the Churches of Zealand, Holland, and the whole coaſt therabouts haue obtained peace I thinke nothing more profitable, and more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, for the eſtabliſhing and preſeruing of a right gouernement in them, then are the things which I haue handled in this Commentarie. For euen as the contempt and neglect of the Churche Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, hath brought ruine vnto the Churche: ſo the carefull obſeruation thereof, beeing orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned according vnto the rule of the Apoſtles, hath not onelie maintained the ſoundnes and puritie of the heauenly doctrine amongeſt men: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hath amended (and retained in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of GOD) the manners and behauiour of thoſe that profeſſed the name of Chriſt, if at any time they ſeemed to decline from the ſinceritie of their profeſsion.</p>
            <p>To bee ſhorte, this ſelfe ſame Diſcipline is both a moſt ſtrong fortreſſe againſt hereſies and Schiſmes that are comming vppe, and a moſt excellent preſeruatiue, and counterpoyſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that are alreadie growen. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:11438:12"/>I knowe, that your excellencye wants not the meanes to come vnto the knowledge of theſe thinges, by the learned conferences, which you may haue with diuers of great knowledge and learning, and eſpecially with that honorable and worthie man, Phillip Marnixus, the Lord of the mount of Saint Aldegond, &amp; with that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſter of God, M. Taffinne, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I thought it not amiſſe for me, to beſtow this my talent according vnto mine abilitie, vnto the common behoofe and profite of your Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that they may vnderſtand, both what great good will, I beare vnto them from my heart, euen in reſpect of your excellencie, and alſo howe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly I pray vnto the Lord, to vouchſafe them all peace and proſperity.</p>
            <p>To come vnder your ſelfe (moſt noble Prince) it is not vnknowen, how well you haue deſerued, both at the handes of all men profeſſing religion, and eſpecially of our Countrey men in Fraunce. Of whoſe ſafety &amp; preſeruation, both your ſelfe, and that noble Earle your brother, Count Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick (whoſe famous and happy memory, I hope, will neuer decay in Gods Church) haue bene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies eſpeciallye carefull. For by the force and counſell of you two, the French Churches haue bene a long time protected from the moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous crueltie, which by their enemies haue bene offered vnto them, contrary to the lawes of their Countrey, and the cuſtome of all antiquity. In concluſion, your renown, &amp; the commendacions
<pb facs="tcp:11438:12"/>of thoſe exploytes that you haue atchieued, for the defence of gods glory, is ſo rife in the mouths of all men in Chriſtendome, that your match in the conſtant defending of the good cauſe, is not euery where to be found amongſt men. For you haue deliuered the Countrey committed vnto your gouernment, from the tyrannie of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, and all forraine enemies: you haue by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected waies, and almoſt after an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie manner, healed the breaches of the Lowe-countrey, that was lamentablie torne in ſunder by inward broiles and diſcord, and haue reſtored them to their former ancient liberty and honor. You haue put the enemies to flight, being nowe ready to deuide the ſpoil, and carrying before you the enſigne of Chriſtes cauſe, gotten the victorie and triumphed ouer them. You are renowned by all men, as a patrone of godlines and pietie, &amp; the moſt valiant vphoulder of publike iuſtice and peace. So that you which haue done ſo great and ſo excellent things, for the enlarging of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and the defence of the liberties of your Countrey, doe alſo iuſtly deſerue to bee well ſpoken of by all men. For as Euripides ſaith, mens good deedes doe alwaies procure good ſpeches to be vttered in their praiſe and commendacions. As to my ſelfe, right excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince, ſeing I doe vnderſtand, that ſo many of your admirable and worthy actions, are euerie where commended through the world, I thought it my duty, to leaue this worke as a teſtimonie of
<pb facs="tcp:11438:13"/>my dutifull good will towards your excellencie, and of my poore endeuour to publiſh abroad the commendacion of your deſerued praiſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne. The which labour of mine, I earneſtly entreat your excellencie, to accept in good part. The Lord who is God alone, eternal, wiſe, good, juſt and mercifull, ſtrengthen and confirme you, as hee did Daniell with his holy ſpirite, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue you among vs, and eſpecially in the Lowe-countries for the ſupport &amp; defence of his church in quietnes and proſperitie many yeares.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, <date>the calends of Auguſt. 1577.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your excellencies moſt bounden LAMBERT DANAEVS.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11438:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
